Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
learning about orbital diagram
diagrams, which is going to further
illustrate how we can show electron
configuration in a more visual manner.
The big reason why we need to
learn about this is because
with electron configuration,
it can get a little confusing.
Um, but there are three major rules
for how to actually be able to make
sure you are filling everything in
correctly in order for us to go by.
Um, the big reason is when you have a
periodic table and you're trying to read
it to actually assign where electrons go.
It's a little hard.
So the first rule is the Aufbau
principle, which is we always fill
our lowest energy level first.
Um, so we start at the bottom and we go
all the way up to the top, meaning we
start at the 1s orbital, move up to 2s,
then to 2p, and so on, filling as we go.
Now, being that every orbital has so many,
um, or every essentially sub level has so
many orbitals available, One thing we've
got to keep in mind is we can only fit
two electrons in every single orbital.
Okay, so when we are doing
those two electrons, why two?
Well, you've got to think this electron
is this little subatomic particle.
The way to look at it is
think of it as like a ball.
So if I have, let's say, a basketball
and I was trying to spin it on
my finger, well, what direction
could you actually spin it?
Well, the one way to think of that
is right, it can either spin either
counterclockwise, or counterclockwise.
Or you could try to, or start
clockwise or, um, counterclockwise.
when you are trying to do that.
So it's all about which direction
will this thing rotate on when
it's rotating around its axis.
So this is the whole idea of spin.
So when we are writing these in
orbitals, we'll show orbitals as
a little line and we are going
to show the electrons as arrows.
So one of them is going to be going
up, And the other one is going to
be going down to represent spin
up, as we call them, and spin down.
So, now, this is an oversimplification
of the idea, but it's just enough for
us to be able to understand, um, to
understand this concept rather than
diving deep into the quantum mechanics
and understanding how these all work.
Now, the last rule is Hund's rule, which
is essentially when you are writing your
electrons in these orbitals, some of the
orbitals are considered to be degenerate.
Now, what is a degenerate one?
Well, an example of this would be,
let's say, if I had the p orbital.
Uh, so P has three
individual orbitals to it.
Um, it has one on the x axis, one on the
y axis, one on the z axis, if you were
to try to think of this mathematically.
So when we are trying to fill our
electrons in this, We fill one
electron in each individual orbital
first, or we start pairing them up.
Now the reason behind this, while we're
pairing them up, is essentially, it
comes to the analogy I love to use, is
let's say you are to try to Uh, stay
in a house with a bunch of roommates.
Do all of you start kind of, kind
of jamming everybody into just
one bedroom inside the house?
Usually not generally you all want your
own private space, your own private room.
Then you start doubling people
up when you run out of space.
So, when it comes to like the p orbital,
right, you can only fit up to 6 electrons,
but you're going to start putting
somebody in each bedroom first, before
you start filling up everything, okay?
So, and then once you've run out of
room, you then go to the next floor
and start filling that up as well.
Starting off, let's start off strong.
What does this entire picture look like?
Well, uh, right here, what I have shown is
essentially a complete orbital diagram for
an atom that could have, let's say it had
the maximum number of electrons possible.
Every single one of these orbitals is all
the ones possible in your periodic table.
So you can see on the far left
in yellow we have S, in purple we
have P, and then in blue we have
D, and then F we have in green.
Now, with these, it's a very common
question that you get asked on homeworks.
Um, is in order to either draw these
or to try to list them in order.
Now keep in mind we're always
going to have our little rules
that are here with us, right?
The first thing is how do you decide
where do electrons go in this entire mess?
Well, remember, rule number one,
the Aufbau principle, electrons
always start in their lowest level.
So, one way to help you try
to remember how to start this
is use the diagonal method.
So, the diagonal method, this
is a chart that you can download
anywhere on the internet if you look
up diagonal method for electrons.
You'll find it.
You can find it in any textbook.
The way it works is it's written
in a very specific order.
Notice how every single row
has the same quantum number.
Now, keep in mind, you're doing
diagonal, meaning how we're
going to show this, we'll start
in the corner, we go up, right?
So one S two would be first.
We then go to two s two.
We do that one up and we
keep doing diagonals across.
to show how all these are done in order.
So we go from tails to heads.
All right.
So just to kind of illustrate
how does that work.
So if you look at how I started it,
right, I went 1s2, then I went to here,
right, so tails, up to 2s2, then I
went to 2p6, to 3p, 3s2, then to 3p6,
then to 4s2, 3d10, and so on, right?
We can show how that order is as
we are representing this based on
what we are seeing here, right?
So we can write down the entire thing,
um, as far as we need to, to put that
order based on the diagonal method.
And this can keep going.
All the way through, through the entire
thing, um, to complete that picture.
So, using the diagonal method is a
really, really easy way to remember this.
Now, keep in mind, most professors and
teachers do not give you this on exams.
So, it's something that you kind of
got to memorize how to put it together.
Just keep in mind, right?
Uh, that these are all going by
their individual, uh, rows of
that periodic table, all right?
When you are going through these,
we're going to be filling them in,
and let's go through some actual
examples for how we can fill in those
electrons using arrows to show it.
The first example is nitrogen.
So nitrogen, the electron
configuration is 1s2.
2s2 2p3.
So what does all this represent?
Well, if you remember from my previous
videos on electron configuration, we
learned that we could find these and
write them based on our periodic table.
We're just learning how to
put them in orbital diagrams.
First thing is all those exponents,
they're representing the total
number of electrons that are here.
So we have seven total electrons.
Now, the way that we're going to put them
in our table here is being that we have
1s2, that's going to be our first orbital.
So we're going to put two
electrons in 1s2, right?
And notice how I did spin up.
Spin down.
So we first followed our Aufbau
principle by starting at the lowest
level and then we did the Pauli
exclusion principle, which is all about
them pointing in opposite directions.
Now being that we just did that
one, what we do next is 2s2.
So we go up, down, like so, and
then we will continue that trend.
So being that now we have 2p3,
well, we don't just automatically
write all six electrons.
We now got to use Hund's rule, which
we have degenerate orbitals here.
So we're going to assign each
electron gets their own room, okay?
So being that you have three
rooms available, why not put
an electron in each one first?
And when we do this, they all point
in the same direction, either all
pointing up or all pointing down.
You choose, as the artist, they all
gotta be pointing in the same direction.
And one thing you can check for yourself
is, do you have seven arrows, right?
So you can kind of see here, I have
one, two, I have three, four, and
then I have five, six, seven, right?
So I have all of my arrows.
here.
Um, we can also use the count valence
electrons really easily as well.
If you remember, valence is your
outermost shell, so everything that is
in the two group here, which is your
highest quantum number, is your valence.
So that means in this case we have
Five valence electrons and two
core electrons for this example.
Let's go on to the next.
Sodium is 1s2, 2s2, 2p6, 3s1.
So now what we are going to be
doing is filling in our, filling
in our orbitals once again.
So we first start with 1s2.
We are going to put our two
electrons into that orbital.
They're now accounted for.
We'll go on to two S two, which is
now our next lowest energy level.
We will fill in both of those.
We'll move on to two P
six, then to three s.
And as a result, remember, we're
filling one electron in each orbital
first because of Hund's rule.
Now we're going to come back and
fill in the remainder because
we have, as you can see, we have
six electrons in that orbital.
So we're going to put all
six in there as we go.
Then for 3s, we only have one
single electron, being that's the
lowest possible available, we will
put one electron in that level.
It's like so.
Now this is a orbital
diagram for sodium, okay?
We can also still do the little
math too for ourselves, how many
valence electrons do we have?
So once again, you're going to
look, what is your highest level?
So we have three here,
that is your highest one.
So we have one valence electron, across,
um, all the other electrons here.
So you can see we have a total
of 11 total electrons, but one of
them is in your outermost level.
So phosphorus, we're going
to do the same general idea.
We're going to start from the bottom.
So we start at 1s, and we're going
to put our first two electrons in.
And notice how it's a pattern, right?
We're going in the exact
same order every time.
So 1s2, 2s2.
So we have both of those completed.
Now we're going to go to 2P6 and the 3S2.
So we're following Aufbau principle
by doing the lowest first.
And we're also doing Paul Exclusion
Principle by doing the opposite spins.
Notice how we're doing Hund's Rule by
doing, filling in the whole orbital first.
Then we do our s.
Okay, now, so 3p, so
notice how we have 3p3.
So how should we fill
this in with Hund's Rule?
Well, keep in mind being that
these are all degenerate orbitals
when we have our p orbital.
So we're going to put
essentially one individual in
each room first for phosphorus.
And this is how we do an
orbital diagram for phosphorus.
We go through and we fill, fill in
one at a time until, you know, until
we don't have any electrons left.
And we can even go through
and count them as well, right?
You can see there's a total of 15
electrons for this, for this atom.
So 15 total.
And we can see that we have five
valence electrons available.
Let's go on to our next example.
Okay, so sometimes a more realistic
example that you might have to come across
is writing the orbitals from scratch
where they're not there for you, which
can prove to be a challenging problem.
But we have the diagonal method
here, so how exactly can you do this?
Now, depending on your, your examples
that you have, you don't always have to
write this in order of, um, going from
bottom to top showing the energy levels.
Sometimes you can also write them in,
in like from left to right horizontal
as well, as long as you're labeling and
showing how does the energy increase.
So in this case, an example, if I
want to go from left to right, we're
gonna do the same thing as before We
start at the one s and we are going
to write those two electrons in one s.
Next we have two s, so we'll
write our one orbital for two s.
What are arrows?
We'll start go to two P and then three x.
Now at two P, we have three orbitals
here, one in each going across.
And then 3p5, we will fill 3 across
and then come back with 2 electrons.
Now, looking closely at this one, what
is, what are some things to notice
in terms of counting the electrons?
Another thing to talk about is
paired and unpaired electrons.
So, one thing you can see is that
there are many paired electrons here,
so anything that's paired is when you
have two electrons going up and down.
Unpaired is when you have a lonely
electron that's by itself in a room.
So for this particular example,
we have one unpaired electron.
Okay, so there's many different ways.
Now, one of the things when you have an
unpaired electron, It generally means that
that atom will have a tendency to either
want to lose electrons to get rid of it,
or to gain electrons to get rid of it.
They don't like having lonely electrons.
They all want to have a partner.
So for this one, I want to
look at chlorine minus, right?
So chlorine as an anion, or
if you remember, anions are
negative, meaning that we are
going to be gaining an electron.
So how would that happen?
What's going to occur is if you have
a cation or anion you're going to
edit your electron configuration.
So we notice here how it
changed from 3p5 to 3p6.
This shows the gain of one electron.
So that's also going to change
in the electron configuration,
and it's going to change over
here in the orbital diagram, too.
So we'll add an extra arrow to represent,
oh, we now have chlorine, and it
gets rid of that unpaired electron.
Making it paired.
Okay, so that's something
else that can be done as well.
So a couple little tricks here that
are possible to have And we're still
following all our rules as we go through
it So let's take a look at a few more
examples and see what else we can do
as well for this example We are going
to do scandium and particularly we're
going to look at the scandium 2 plus
cation So, how do we go about it?
Well, let's first just draw the neutral
and neutral one first, and then we will,
uh, fill in the rest of the puzzle.
So we're going to use our diagonal
method to help us, so being that
this is a very useful little trick.
So first things first, right, we fill in
our lowest orbital, do that alpha alpha
principle, so we do 1s, And then two s,
and then two P six, um, will be next.
And then we will do three s two.
Now you can, so we did the first few,
so now we're gonna be doing three P, six
to four s and then into the 3D orbital.
So let's fill in all of our electrons.
Alright, now being that we have scandium
two plus, where do we take the electrons?
So how exactly does this work?
So when we have a cation where
the electrons are going to be
taken from the outermost layer.
Now what is your outermost layer?
This is from your valence electrons.
So cations lose valence electrons first.
Okay, so that's very, very
important to remember.
We lose the valence first.
So what are your valence
electrons in this case?
Well, it's not 3D, believe it or not.
It is the 4s electrons are
your highest level, right?
It has the highest quantum number, meaning
they're the ones on the outside layer.
So, being that when we do this for
our configuration, We are going to
take away the electrons from 4s,
even though it was written earlier,
it still had the higher number.
So that's going to go away and we're
going to take that out and erase it.
Okay, and it's only going to have 3d1.
So we'll remove those electrons
from that orbital leaving it.
Empty as a result.
Okay, so they disappear first and that's
because four is greater than three
Okay, so four is a greater atomic or
not atomic quantum number than three.
All right Let's take a look
at another weird quirky rule.
So this is known as the
exception rule All right.
Our last example is about the
exception rule So there are
some exceptions to how electron
configuration and orbital diagrams
can work in terms of the Pirog table.
There's two exceptions that can
be found, and it's on the column
with chromium and the column
with copper in your Pirog table.
So the chromium and copper families.
So let's say if we look at the
first one, which is chromium.
So I wrote its noble gas
configuration here, which is 4s2 3d4.
Now, if you kind of notice with
the degeneracy here, well, I wrote
we have four electrons by itself,
and we have these two electrons
over here that are together.
Well, it doesn't seem like there's
anything bad, but there's one thing that
these have a tendency to want to do.
Notice how there is this
empty room all by itself.
And these guys, and these
two guys over here, these two
brothers, have to share a room.
Well, it's like, oh, I can move
upstairs and have my own room.
That's what is actually going to happen.
So with this, let's kind of change
the colors here a little bit.
We can have where one of these
electrons is actually going to end up
moving over here to this other level.
Now, all six electrons here all have their
own individual orbitals all to themselves.
So, the configuration is
going to change as a result.
It's no longer going to be a 4s2 3d4.
Instead, we're going to
have argon, or S1, 3d5.
So this only happens if the chromium in
copper rho So copper's the same idea.
So notice how I have four S, two, 3D nine.
We're also gonna have it where instead
it wants to do four S one 3D 10.
Let's try to take a look at that.
So it's these elements on
here, on the purac table.
So the one thing to keep in mind is
you never ever want to write S 2D four.
or S2D9.
So maybe like put them on
a flash card for yourself.
If you see yourself writing it down,
that is one of the exception rules.
So it's these five elements here.
So it's chromium's column, if you
remember it that way, and copper's column.
It's an easy way to notice it, being that
it's at the ninth spot in the fourth row.
It's the only time these happen.
It's very common to get chromium or
copper on an exam or a homework, just and
you have to be aware of the exception.
Alright, so this is all
of Orbital Diagrams.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video
helped you a little bit.
Try to understand a little bit
more of electron configuration.
How do we draw electrons?
How can we try to actually put
them in their own unique boxes?
And there will be more content to come.
Thank you so much.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button if you haven't yet.
And I will see you all later.
Bye now.